Okay.
Alright.
Got it.
So,
I'm going to call to order the town of Andover,
board of selectmen special meeting, budget workshop for Monday,
January 29.
It is, 07:01PM,
and our first order of business is the pledge of allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of The United States Of America
and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible,
with liberty and justice for all.
Okay, public speak. Jay, would you like to speak?
>> Sure. Alright. We're gonna get right into the budget. Let's go.
>> Alright. Before before we go, Eric,
before we let you go, Jay. Eric, you sent us this budget.
Yep. Can we go to your main page?
So or, your mill rate calculation page first.
Yep.
Okay.
So Let me pull it up.
Yeah.
>> Okay. So your your current information,
calls for a $600,000
total expenditure
increase, $609.06
54. Right?
And then we have, an estimated revenue increase of a $175,400,
potential use of fund balance of a $100,000.
And I wanna make sure I understand the abatement exemptions is a reduction
in taxes, right, that we provide to the firemen or to other organizations. What's that what's that related to?
>> Right.
So there should be a number assigned to that. When I put out the original budget, I didn't have the abatement list for the fire department.
There are two things that get abatements.
The first is,
the fire department members who work a certain amount of calls.
Yeah. And the second is the abatement for the Hop River Homes. Those are the two things that fall under abatements and exemptions.
So
>> that in essence is a reduction in revenue, correct? Correct.
Okay.
Alright.
>> I
just don't have an accurate number for what that is.
That's an outstanding question for John.
And then I did get the list the other day from the fire department, so I should be we should be able to calculate their portion of it.
>> Okay. So what I, what I'm driving at is, I want to make sure I work with you to make sure that our spreadsheets add all the way through what we're doing, because
it concerns me when I look at this and I, and I, I'm looking at it going,
okay, we have,
what we're what we're talking about proposing is an extra $609,000
of expenditures
reduced by a $175,000
of additional revenue.
And and I just need everybody to understand that as we're talking about this, because that's the biggest thing I think that we all have to get on the same page as to
what is our threshold.
We want to do all these things, but it's gonna end up being,
you know, and I'm okay doing it. I really will tell you. I'm okay doing what Eric is asking for. I'm okay with the person at the scene, the community center.
But we have to have the right number so we're all on the same page because it's not a small amount of money. And and I don't want the the way that the spreadsheet is is calculated to throw anyone off.
So,
okay. That was it. I I wanted to understand what that exemption was, and I think the number
is somewhere right now around $400,000
if you use the $100,000
in fund balance.
So okay.
>> I'm looking at total dollars. Okay, Jay. Now let's go to you.
So, Jay, spend less. Alright?
>> Okay.
I'll do my best.
Alright.
Alright. I got the screen moved over to my big screen so I can see what I'm doing.
Alright. So I'm assuming Eric sent you everything that I sent him
in regards to
my my spreadsheet,
my email notes, or anything like that, or just want me to go over
each budget?
I mean, we're gonna go over it, but I'm just what are what are you seeing so I know what you're looking at?
Starting with the operating,
budget and snow budget.
>> Eric, did you send us that? And am I missing looking at what?
>> As far as I know, I sent you all of that. Tell me the email that's related to it.
>> There's one email with about 10 or 12 attachments.
Mhmm.
It was on January 23.
>> Thank you.
No. That's king.
Oh, working copy of the budget. My bad. My bad. Go ahead. I I was opening up the other one.
Okay.
Don't you Can you share your screen?
>> You
may as well. Yep.
Let me, I'll bring up my
post disabled
participant screen sharing so I can't
>> Hang on. Give me two seconds.
Okay. Try it now.
>> Alright.
Share.
Alright. Let me bring up operating
budgets.
You might have to walk me through this
because I've only done it a couple times. So I got my
operating budget. Now I gotta share it. Right?
>> Yep.
So if if you've said share screen,
if you've clicked on the green button on the bottom that says share screen
Yep.
>> There we go. Okay. It should show you whatever windows are open. You just pick the right one.
How's that?
You're seeing anything?
Yep. Yep. Okay.
>> So I'm gonna expand on that.
All right. So this is the spreadsheet that I use
once I get my final numbers
from you and from the Board of Finance.
For my operating,
I am
asking for $4.50.
Well, let me back up a little bit.
So salary and full time, you're going to have to take salary
and wages. You're going to have to take that out of it, the equation, because
Eric has all those numbers. I just kind of assumed
things.
So
basically, we're just looking at,
you know, vehicle maintenance, supply shop, the stuff that I take care of, stuff on your end, you know, you're gonna have to back that out of it because I didn't have that information at the time when I was making this. All
>> of all of his employees except for Jay, our union.
Correct. So all contractually rated increases that we have to deal with. Right. What is a variable
>> is
the overtime, how much we allot for overtime.
And the second variable is temp salary,
which covers if we're using somebody other than a public works employer employee for a road guard.
Yeah.
>> And sometimes, you know, we'll use
the guys from the transfer station because one of them is
qualified
as their roadguard license.
And,
you know, we'll ask them for help once in a while.
So that being said,
if you look in there, I tried to put in last year's budget
or allotments
and what I'm asking for this year in each category.
As you go through so right now,
let's look at vehicle maintenance.
Alright. Vehicle maintenance
on your end, you see a one number line item,
which I take your number and I break it up a little bit because I try to keep some money set aside for specific reasons.
So it's the same number,
our same account number,
but it's, you know, I just break it up.
So in this year's budget,
I asked for a flat
budget increase on the maintenance vehicle maintenance,
but I asked for more money in tires,
which increased the totality
of
maintenance
equipment maintenance.
Specifically,
we have two trucks that are actually three trucks, two are our big dump trucks need rear tires and our five fifty needs tires all the way around.
If you click on
tires maintenance, well, it's me.
All right. So you'll see that I gave an explanation
at the future expenditures
for tire maintenance.
That's the cost of the tires.
We have the ability to use
state bid pricing for Firestone tires,
which are a little lesser quality.
We would save not quite $200
a tire.
But the Michelin's
provide a deeper lug tire,
longer lasting,
and that's really a better way for us to go.
So I
priced out the Michelin's on
for these tires,
just much better handling, longer lasting, heavier tire.
Our front tires are fine.
And, you know, sandblast, what we would do is we would take some existing tires and wheels,
get rid of the tires
and sandblast
our, you know, wheels get little rusty and crusty. So we like to get them repainted.
Alright,
so let's go back to summary.
Any questions on that?
>> In your spreadsheet, just so I understand this, when I look on the detailed tab for tire maintenance, you have a surplus in the deficit.
That's what you expect not to spend?
>> Yeah. Well, I'd like to keep a $2,500,
surplus.
So I increased
typically we hold about $2,500
for tires.
Yeah.
So I'd like to keep that because,
you know, we'll have tire maintenance throughout the year.
If we have a flat tire, I know that our chipper needs tires that that'll probably be a couple $100 per tire.
And if we get a flat tire like our roadside mower, we usually have some kind of repair or something during the year, the tire,
whatever.
So
the added expense really for tires above the 2,500
>> is the new tires on the trucks. Okay, understood. I get what you're doing.
>> Okay. So back to our summary page. Now we move into supplies.
And if you look at supplies,
supplies
in totality
is 19,500.
And if you look how I break it up,
supply shop I increased by
$500
Seems like we never were borderline either having enough or not having enough each year, so I added $500
this year.
Lubes and filters,
kept flat.
Supply sweeper, I brought it up a couple $100.
Uniform and safety, we have a little bit more in uniform costs here this year because of
increase of, uniform,
rentals,
and I can bring that up.
So this is my breakdown for uniforms
through the year.
We also have
PPE
is our if we needed gloves for state equipment,
stuff to I try to keep a little extra as a buffer in there for PPE.
Rain gear, sometimes we rip our rain gear, gotta get to safety
shoes,
and then our
difference in uniforms
throughout the year.
So come March, there's a 3% increase. So that's what the increase is.
That's kind of the breakdown for our supplies
on uniforms.
So supplies,
break up in,
one, two, three, four
four categories.
Right?
Yep.
Any questions on that?
>> Is the per is the maintenance
budget will that
can we expect that to go down when the as the fleet gets newer and newer, or is it always gonna stay the same? Well, this year
>> hang on a second. We're doing pretty good on maintenance.
Yeah. That's the hope, Scott.
And we're doing pretty well with that right now.
I'm gonna bring that up on the side here, and I'll tell you where we're at.
But we're still
see. Still fixing older vehicles.
>> Yeah. You know, so right now,
I just reconciled.
Had
vehicle maintenance. Okay. So we had 29,000
again.
And right now we've spent
6,500.
We've got a surplus currently,
by my calculations,
right around $22,000
We have,
I just put in for I bought some supplies.
You know, one of the things that we've been working on since I started was,
you know, having a better stock of
items to repair equipment, you know, in event of emergency.
So
we just spent
$9.07,
call it $1,600
on just
hardware to repair battery
cables, electrical cables, you know, the the ends.
There's all different shapes, sizes,
you know, just so we're pecking away at things.
I don't have any big ticket items right now between now and the end of the year.
Excuse me, for maintenance. So,
you know, I'm just keeping an eye on that. Our tires right now,
I'm just a little over. We actually spent 4,500
in tires this year.
Answer to your question is yes. We're working on that, but we're not quite there yet that we're gonna,
I don't think we're quite ready to
lower.
You're still fixing everything.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. We did some maintenance on the chipper this year. We got that running better.
So, you know, we're doing pretty good, actually, I I think in the maintenance end of things.
All right.
So moving on
back to the summary page.
So equipment.
Well, miscellaneous labor,
I just brought it up to $1,800
We have
rented some equipment
if we bring in somebody to give us a hand
if we need to, but basically this is
rental. So we've had, did some utilize some renting some equipment this year. I'd like to do it again
if it works out.
We started screening our own loan.
If we can set that aside and we continue to bring
loam spoils in and we stock it at our pit and we screen our own loam because that's kind of expensive,
expenses,
expensive,
sorry.
And, you know, that way we don't have to purchase it.
Let's see.
Tools. Tools were running about the same. We spend about the same amount of money each year. We're pretty good there. Left that flat. You know, we're
we're gaining on that as well. We got a pretty good supply of shop tools. We, you know, continually to upgrade some of our abilities.
So we look to buy something for our shop
or what we need out in the field
in the way of hand tools and miscellaneous
items.
Equipment
signs.
So
signs
is something we'll bring up now and we can, know, bring it up later as well.
Signs, traffic control equipment, cones, barrels,
you know, we've been doing improvements here and there, pecking away at that as well.
As a town,
a whole,
need to address our signage.
And we kind of started this year,
did some couple of intersections. I don't know if you've noticed
Hendy, Long Hill.
We upgraded the signage in there. We're kind of starting with stop signs, warning signs ahead.
You know, we really need to get into our speed limit signs.
And
having them placed properly on our roadways
and then into our warning signs as we go along,
Hoping the state comes in with,
I don't know, we applied for a grant not too long ago or a program that they were going to help us with some warning signs and we got a
communication that,
you know, it's still a go, and we're on the list. They just don't have no idea when it's gonna happen. But I figure if we start with stop signs and warning signs ahead and speed limits, that's a good good way to start.
And I I'm gonna address that again in our capital
improvements as well.
So I'd like to see a little bit more money in signage if we can do that.
And the total for equipment tools,
I have it as $8,000.
So,
and then,
our radios,
you know, we're gonna have to we're gonna that's another day. You know, we we know that our communication is subpar.
We're having difficulties on
the North End of town.
You know, Gilead
at the North Side.
Gilead and no, that's South Side.
Gilead,
Jarrabadi,
Burnout, all that area of town, it's like a dead zone for us.
>> Jake, quick question.
Yep. How has the buses changing frequency and going their own way affected you?
>> We have no communication with them whatsoever.
I was alerted to that a couple of weeks ago.
I asked, if we would be able to get the frequency,
whether we would be able to
our radios. I haven't heard anything as of yet,
but we have absolutely no communication with them.
If they were to get into a little bit of a bind somewhere,
the only thing is I have, you know, pretty good communication
via phone text.
That's all we got.
>> Now did they go
on to the state system
or did they just change frequencies?
>> They changed frequencies.
They're on the frequency that RAM operates on.
Got it.
>> So that's what I'm told.
So that's really all I know about that.
K.
How often have they called you for any issues?
>> Oh, we communicate quite often, actually. You know, if there's a a tree down, a wire down that we know about, I immediately call, bus one.
Some sometimes if I know it's, you know, I know where bus two typically is, I know where bus three typically is, but if you know, most of the time I communicate with bus one,
and she relays to everybody.
And that's who I have phone communication with.
So, you know, it's
a little bit more hiccup in our communication,
our ability to communicate
in a safe manner, or I shouldn't say a safe manner. That's probably the wrong terminology, but you know, just to it's not as efficient. Let's put it that way. It's not as quick.
You know, we have road closures due to whatever
flooding wires down.
You know, I can tell somebody, hey, look,
Wires partially blocking the road. If you're really careful, you can drive the other lane. But, you know, sometimes you gotta do what you gotta do, but that's hard to do when you're talking on the phone and and, trying to communicate
that way. Why did they switch,
I
>> guess basically because of the communication
levels
that they have or the abilities to talk to each other.
So now
that they're on the same frequency with
RAM, through RAM,
you know, they can hear Marlboro,
Hebron, you know, they can all talk together,
which leaves
us out of the loop.
>> Well, let's let's last year we talked about potentially the state system.
Yes.
And so upgrade to that. Yeah.
Eric, that is something that probably should just be addressed, you know, in capital, our capital budgeting, if, you know, it's necessary and we wanna do that.
So
>> Yeah. I mean, would that even help you? I I guess I guess let's make this a little more efficient. I went through and I I
you know,
your your total in this segment of your budget, your total increase is $28,000.27
$8.84
22.
Yep.
>> And of that,
you know, the biggest, the two biggest components are the, the fuel
13.9%.
It's, increase of, of, of $4,000.38
75.
Anybody have any questions on that? I'm assuming, Jay, that that's
are you are you determining you're using more fuel or just higher price?
Both.
>> Most of most of it is just higher price.
Actually, I take that We're a little bit less this year than last year.
>> So we have had some increases in fuel usage.
So part of the issue too is that we have ended the last two years
with absolutely
bone dry tanks,
have either had to put a little fuel in at the end at market price
or went into the following year with zero in our diesel tanks.
And so I added a thousand dollars to our total or a thousand gallons to our total usage
this year when we signed the contract,
because I want a little bit of buffer at the end of the year.
I'm not planning on getting back to full full tanks,
but we should have a little left at the end of the year.
>> So so all that extra usage, we'll just blame on Paula and her ride alongs.
They
are very important and informative.
>> Absolutely.
I'll give it to you. Alright. So,
alright. So that's that's one
that's one
of the larger
pieces on this. And then you have tire maintenance is tire maintenance, which is 18.63%,
and you at least provided us that those details there.
So
anybody have a problem with the tire maintenance?
No? Okay. And then the the biggest piece of the whole thing was,
salaries.
And so Eric,
that is a $16,000
increase, and that is all contractually related. Right?
>> So
that
is
correct.
The so
it is all contractually related except for Jay Tunnel's salary
Yes. Which is set by you as a board of select.
>> K. And and is that included in it $3.37
currently?
>> So that's not the actual number. The actual number is, which is what is in the budget
is $3.33
or $3.32
$4.59
>> for public work salary line up. All right. So we'll go over that separately
in a different, a different time because I saw Jay's email.
I, I guess what I'm, I'm after is does anyone have anything specific
for Jay? Because his overall increases aren't
that,
you know, you know, listen, Jay, I'm just telling you, in my head, the biggest thing we're gonna end up coming back to you on is in total.
Like, if the board sits there and looks at the increase,
in total of $600,000
we may come back to your budget because it's such a significant portion of what we do and say, hey, Jay, we're gonna have to cut $10,000
$20,000 $50,000
and I'm just throwing you out numbers,
to get our overall budget
increase
to a more manageable number for their community. And that's all we'd be doing. So I'm just asking the board, does anybody, because what he's providing us,
you know, he's not doing it as detailed as I might want. I might want each one of these tabs with what he's expecting in here in just global terms. Like, if you went through each tab,
Jay, not every tab's filled out, but I don't necessarily need it when it's
a 2.4%
increase, $625
of your total
escalation.
So
>> Yeah. It's I mean, it I'm just showing you know, I showed what we had last year,
you know, in
as approvals
and my increases, you know, or flat,
it would be this year.
Now
>> I would ask you, Jay, from your spreadsheet perspective, because you could add it in differently. You can't you can't access that cell because you typed in that cell that gives me last year's number. You have to put that number in its own cell so that you can calculate on it. Okay. Right? So I'm I'm just letting you know. So I broke all those out. So,
you know, what he's talking about here in his operating segment is a total increase of $627,000.
And I'm not gonna
Eric has a different number that will go into budget. And as long as it's less, it's fine. It's $27,884.28
is the total
increase
from year to year.
And
biggest components are wages, which are contractual,
the tires
that he's discussed,
which we absolutely need, and the increase in the fuel.
Anybody have any questions on anything specific, or can we,
or do we need them to do anything in more detail? Are we gonna go over the capital budget for?
Yeah, that's a whole other
>> section that I'm assuming we're gonna talk about. Hey, the algae side, is that something that you have to do regularly, Like
No. That's every time? They bring fuel in? Let's just quickly I'll click on diesel.
>> So
I have the tanks tested every year,
And the answer to your question, Scott, is no.
It's not done at this year.
Our water was good. We had no bugs. We didn't have to do algaecide.
And, you know, so we were good. You know, we have the company we use tests our fuel for free.
The only thing that we do when we stay on top of is our fuel additives, make sure we try to, you know, keep our fuel. So,
you know, anti gel and some, know, we have put in some added lubrication because that sulfur fuels a little dry.
So that's kind of the breakdown right here.
On our fuel side,
I like to, you know, a thousand dollars for fuel additives, we usually go through two buckets to five gallon pails at a time
to two and a half pails depending.
Then we have a summer
additive and then our tank maintenance.
Tank maintenance is kind of an unknown,
whether we need
a water pump out.
Last time we did a water was a year before and I think it was
$450
somewhere around there. And we did have
algaecide bugs in it. That would that's like a $300 treatment give or take
depending on, you know, what's needed.
And then just other miscellaneous things, you know, we might need a hose and I know we need a there's a dial up top to figure out what they call it, but
exactly that needs to be replaced in that.
I'm not sure where Eric has this, but
I did get a quote to have our fuel system updated as far as our
software.
Eric, can you say where that is? Is that a good time to bring this up, or is that someplace else at another time?
>> No. We can talk about it. Where did I?
So I put under,
if you look in the notes under the transfers,
one of my notes was that the board should consider adding 12 k to cover the cost of the fuel
system upgrade for public works
under the public works equipment fund.
>> So I didn't have that
in here in my
spreadsheet.
So
I'm assuming everybody's aware we're having issues,
occasional issues, and and
don't ask me why other than this system is really old.
The software program
is not supported
like six times out
from upgrades, we can't even really do anything with it if we wanted to.
And to do an upgrade, it's I have a quote for 12,147.
And that's through equipment service.
And to do a new system?
What's that?
If you wanted to replace the entire system.
>> Oh, that would be big money.
I didn't
last time the last time it was, you know, it was 20.
Yeah.
That was a lot of money. This Well, actually, to tell you the truth, this is replacing the pedestal up front. The only thing it's not replacing, it wouldn't be replacing the pump
because the pump still is operational.
It's just the electronics
and, you know, the the just the software.
We'd have to do a computer upgrade.
I'm not sure whether I can use this.
You know, just have to check with it. I'm not sure whether this computer would support it because I have a separate desktop
dedicated just to this
fuel system. I don't I don't use it for anything but that because I'm scared to use it for anything but that
just because it's so old.
The last time I tried to get back into it to do something, got into some old DOS program and I just like, no, I don't know enough. I'm backing out. See you later. Bye. But we got it to work again the last time it stopped working. So,
yeah,
that's all I gotta say about that.
Can you provide
>> the cost of a brand new system and the cost of the upgraded system?
>> No. This is this is a brand new system.
This isn't an upgrade.
This is The $12,000
is for a software
system.
>> Brand a brand new system. Yes. It it would be a new pedestal out by the pump.
There's a new control panel,
the control panel out there, the one that turns everything on, bells and whistles to make the pump run and activate,
it's outdated. It's working, but it's outdated. So it would be a whole new thing out by the pump.
Cause you put in new
keys,
new fobs so you can
turn the pump. Each vehicle will get a new key,
whole nine yards, and then there would be a new computer software
here,
and it'd all be with CAT,
whatever the cable, you know, we would utilize
the cable that's existing
between the building and the pumps. That cable is okay.
So we wouldn't have to do any underground between
here and the pumps.
We can still utilize was a cat five set in my is that the right terminology?
Cable.
So is that in your budget? This the 12?
>> No, it's not.
I did not put that in this,
because I wasn't sure where this was gonna go.
>> Well, just tell us tell us this so we so I understand.
If the system fails, what happens to you?
>> Every we gotta do everything manually. I gotta ask all the departments to record
every time they come in fuel. They gotta write it down manually. I gotta come up with, you know, everything's
on paper and, you know, doing it on a,
I can't just come sit here behind the desk and click on it and bring up everybody's,
know, when I do monthly reports for fuel
reports and calculate what the cost is.
And right now I calculate the cost. The only thing I get from anybody's report
is gallons used.
I don't get,
you know, the
I can't go into the system
and
put it the actual cost
and have it already calculated
to gallons to cost and then hand it to the finance department,
you know, to Chris at the office.
So how old is this system, Jay?
>> Since
whenever it got put in.
So I, to be honest with you, I don't I don't know how many years ago that was. I'd have to look it up.
So it's whenever you
went whenever you changed over from the the gas and diesel pumps on the side of the building and brought everything out front.
So a long time.
Right.
>> Okay.
So,
Eric, the assumption is that that would be
>> part of CIP's,
CIP request?
So if you decide you wanna fund it, then yes, that would go through. That would probably be a CIP
expense.
But the question becomes what budget do you want to put that through?
Because although
it's related to public works,
public works is not the biggest user of diesel.
The school is the biggest user of diesel total.
It's basically public works plus the fire department plus the school.
>> Okay. So so so just just because now I I, you know, I I'm I
if we did this, well, and and it's part of the pump to sit there, aren't we billing the school for the actual diesel they use?
Yes.
Okay. Are we billing any other entities within the town other than public works for the diesel they use?
>> We bill the school,
we bill RAM, and we bill the fire department for their respective diesel use.
>> Okay. And so why, why, if you know, let's sit there and say that you want to, amortize the cost of the software over three years,
why couldn't you sit there and determine an amount to put on top of the per gallon rate
so that we can sit there and get this
upgrade covered?
I mean, you could, it's just like
>> public works usually incorporates
in their budget, the cost of algaecide
and the diesel additive that is used by everybody.
But again, it's all coming from the same pool of money. So it's just, to me, it's semantics where you fund it, you decide to fund it or you don't decide to fund it.
>> Understood. But if if
if we chose to,
could amortize
those costs into the per gallon price that's charged
to any entity.
We certainly could. If that's how you want to recoup the costs, we could certainly do that. Well, I'm just asking the general question so that we could do that if we chose to, or we could sit there and send it to CIP
and say it's a town. I mean, it's if it's not under public works, then what's it under?
Right? It's
so that was your question. What were we putting it under?
What department would we put this under?
>> So then
I mean, I could see that legitimately either going under the building maintenance fund or the public works equipment fund.
Those are the two funds most likely
to
that that would be applicable to.
>> Okay.
So
if we put it under public works, as long as it doesn't impact negatively impact
the view
of of the community,
or something that's used by the
whole town.
Like, I would sit there and think it would be something to put under the general
general town,
because it's everybody, it's all the organizations.
So,
like, I know what you're saying. I would I would if you put it under public works,
just as long as it doesn't visually take away from,
like, a
what public works might need for overall equipment,
then it's fine.
But, yes, I I I I am actually happy that
Jay told me that it could still run even if the software breaks down.
So,
no, I know you need a new system, Jay, but at least I know you're not gonna collapse and the trucks aren't gonna go.
>> Yeah. I mean, right now, if the software were to
go by the wayside,
just have to Each department has to do manual
recordings and
we do the best with what we have.
Gotcha.
5¢ a gallon till it's paid off.
>> Well, that's just spreading around tax dollars from different places. It's just, you know,
I agree.
I mean, it is a way for everybody that's
participating in this to understand that this is a piece of equipment that's necessary to continue to operate the diesel pumps.
But
it's
The
>> other thing that this system gives me is
I
have to manually go out and stick that tank every week. I can just in the office, I can push a button and it'll tell me how many gallons I have in that tank. So,
you know, after a month or so after my order,
I can come in here and push on the button and start watching
the usage. When I get to about
1,500,
1,200 gallons, I usually order the next, batch.
>> But I would I would also assume that the new system
would be able to give you transactional details by vehicle as to. Yes. And I have that now.
>> But,
you know, so that's another part of the system
that,
you know, you can look back and say, hey, why is this vehicle using so much fuel or whatever? We don't do that now. We just do totality and what because
I don't I don't want to break the system on trying to figure all that stuff out.
And not that we really need to because we're, you know, we're kind of a small,
department,
so it's not that critical
>> to do something like that. Would be able to get through this year without this piece of software.
Yeah.
Hopefully.
>> Yep. Well, I mean, it it has stopped working for a fairly extended period at least once in the last year.
Oh, yeah. How long was that system down for?
The last time?
Yeah.
Almost three months.
>> Yeah. So this has not been the system that has been reliable.
What got it up and running?
>> A hammer.
I don't know, Jeff.
Had the company come out.
They went through the pedestal upfront. We started checking things on the software in here and pushing buttons and wiggling wires.
The guy left and charged us $112
for the service charge. Nothing happened. And the following week I says, You know what? I'm going to start moving wires
and stuff.
It started working again. I don't know.
>> Just So it's not
the software on
the computer, it's something with the hardware? Because you said the CAT five cable is working okay, but I'm just trying to Yeah,
>> there's two
systems here. There's
the recording of There's
the tank monitoring system,
and then there's the
software
that
gets all the readings from the pump
that,
you know, the information for each vehicle as you key in.
So there's two systems
here that are supposed to talk to each other. Well, apparently,
they stopped talking to each other, and they didn't
I
don't know which one. I'm sure it's a software because that's been an issue before.
Sometimes I'll I'll key up a report
and
it magically appears at the at the end of the day. Sometimes I'll key up a report and it's in instantaneous.
I you know, I don't know. I don't I don't understand it. I can't tell you why.
But,
and sometimes,
in the past, I
it says error error, and I just shut it off. And a day later, come back, I turn it on, and it works again. I don't know what
>> it is. Okay. So we all know we have to do this. It's just a question of when. So you have that number. It's a question of when,
not if it's gonna end up having to get done.
Okay.
What else are Okay. Going
So,
let me back out of this.
Give me one second.
K. So now we want
snow budgets.
>> One more question for you on that, Jay. Yep. If if we go or when and if we go with that upgrade,
will you need a new computer or are you gonna be able to put it on the computer that you're using right now?
>> I don't know.
Like, you know, this this desktop,
I I don't have an answer to that.
They
whether it's would support them
I mean this, what is this?
I don't know, it says Windows Vista.
So it's an old desktop. So I would
venture to say no.
But I don't know. That would be a question for the IT department, I guess.
Just be a it just be a desktop. It'd be nice to have a dedicated a dedicated
desktop
just for the fuel system. So it's not
that it's hooked up separately from,
you know, my operating computer here.
>> Jay, this is Jeff. I just,
I'd like to meet with you sometime and take a look at the existing system that you have there.
Yeah,
I know a lot of stuff about fuels managers and tanks and use things. Do a lot of that for my
day job. So there's a lot of stuff out in the market right now that's really reliable,
especially ultrasonic tank monitoring.
You can tell the use just by the level of the tank, and it can get down to within a half a millimeter of tank levels. You can calculate the tank
curvature and the shape, and it will calculate your fuel use per fill.
So there is some stuff on the market that's like non contact that works a lot better than the older stuff. So there may be some options out there for, you know, pretty reasonable prices.
Okay.
>> Yeah. And for the record, I think that tank was installed
in 2008.
And since Windows Vista was launched in 2007,
and that's what that's on that computer,
I suspect that's probably a a 2008
PC
that's in use. So it's
>> there's no way we're recycling that thing. Too old and primitive. Yeah. Let's take a look at it. That's way overdue for an upgrade.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Like I said, it's it's six, seven times
beyond
any
software updates that's even supported by the current company that this, system is.
>> Yeah. We should be updating those every five to seven years at a minimum, so we should probably update that machine.
>> Yep.
Right. But the thing is is that
the
pedestal and the equipment itself is so old, it only runs on Windows Vista.
We couldn't put a modern laptop there and run that system.
That that I thought was the the major problem with it. It all had to be done at once.
>> All right. Any other questions on that?
In my snow budget
or our snow budget?
So again, wages
over time, that's a contract, you know, that's I just added.
Here we go. I added 5% to last year.
So.
Where
I I increased
a little bit from previous year.
Which we had it at 66
to 50 increase to $250,
bringing up to an even number.
Sand,
same.
Just if
we ever have to purchase any sand, it'd be nice to I mean, we have a current sand pile now
that kind of just
this number just rolls over every year.
But
if we do have a need to buy sand for any reason, we have a little bit of money for that.
Plow blades flat
sanding equipment.
I brought that up this year a little bit to $800
from $5.50 last year.
We just have,
you know, miscellaneous
winter items,
equipment items that
we buy. We we tend to spend that money
every year.
So and
we tend to run out a little bit, so I increased it a little bit.
Meals,
I brought up the $7.50.
Building ice maintenance, which is our
bag salt for site. I actually
>> brought the meals
budget
up
more than that because we have a contractual increase in what we pay for the meals based on the union contract.
That was the first increase in, you know,
three rounds of contracts.
So
it had been stagnant for like twelve years,
and now it's gone up to reflect what's closer to current meal costs.
Okay.
What's so would you increase that to?
So I increased the total line item meals
to eight fifty,
which is about an 18%
contract increase, which is roughly what was built into the per meal cost.
>> Okay.
Alright. I can change that on my end.
Building ice maintenance,
which is, the bag salt for the buildings.
Usually buy a pallet of that every year.
This year we're doing okay. I'll have some leftover,
but
I left that flat.
And pretty much
it's it's a flat budget with some minimal increases
on salt.
Salt, we tend to and and I don't have the answer to this question. Hopefully you can provide that to me.
So we tend to budget for like 800 ton a year
or
I should say
contract for 800 ton.
We're running between
last year we purchased
400,
a little over 400 ton, I think it was.
But whatever we
contract
for, we're obligated to buy at least half of that.
So
fortunately, we haven't
gone over
our
budget allotment for salt in the past few years. We've always stayed under.
But if we get a bad year, we could go over a little bit.
But seemingly, this is a pretty decent number
for now.
And salt did go down just a few dollars
a ton this year. So that's a good thing.
Any questions on snow?
Nope.
Alright.
>> Get rid of that one.
EPW
building.
Bring that up.
Garage.
K. Everybody seeing it?
Nope.
No. Oh, I gotta push the share button.
Hang on.
Share.
>> How about now?
Yep.
Okay.
Alright. Phys physicals,
I increased
because physicals have gone up to $150
plus
for everybody.
So I brought that up
last year.
So for five guys,
you know, give or take
$750
Not every not all of us have to go every year, but, some of us are every two years, but there are some that have to go every year.
Training conferences,
seminars flat.
Building maintenance,
I left that flat.
This year,
we are
question?
We got a question.
>> No, that was just me clicking back on. I apologize. Okay.
>> This year, we're going to use up just about everything we have in building maintenance. We had a couple of unforeseen
large ticket expenses.
But I was kind of hoping that
we could
do some other things. But, you know, we had an alarm panel that went south and
but
we didn't get to do some of the electrical upgrades that I'd like to
take care of in this building.
Just kind of put them off till next year. And we've been picking away at electrical issues and just making things a little bit better around here. So we'll just I left that flat.
Furnace maintenance flat,
alarm systems,
internet cable that hasn't changed. I mean, the their bill is the same. Electricity,
I don't really I just gave an increase here
of
I added 5%.
I'm not sure if that's really accurate. I don't see the electrical bills. It's just when we reconcile,
I'll see what they are and I just put them into my budget as I get them.
So
if that seems within the realm,
I just added 5% to electricity.
Heating oil, left flat.
>> Going back to electricity,
I actually dropped in the overall budget,
the electrical budget for the town hall down to 5,400
because
it looks like we've gotten through the big spike in electrical costs.
We budgeted
6,700,
but we spent
considerably
under that.
And looking at today's numbers, I think 5,400
should cover it.
>> For,
DPW?
Correct.
Okay.
Alright. So we can drop that 5,400.
Alright.
>> Heating oil,
I left the same.
Again, that's something that's a variable that I don't see.
Office supplies flat, computer flat,
and that's what I have for a building.
>> Yeah, and if the board wants to see separately the calculations
for fuel, oil, electricity,
I can give you those spreadsheets separately
because I did go through
looking at both diesel and,
you know, heating fuel oil usage for all the public buildings
and then backed it out to what our current
rate would be.
>> Eric, are any of these line items significantly
over budget or under budget in the current year?
So Because that's what you could do for us as we move on to other departments, as we talk about the other departments,
is identifying what's significantly
over budget or under budget. Because
what Jay's doing here is just giving us their flatty, flatty, flatty, And we really have no exposure to
where he's currently at. Like he said, he doesn't see the bills, but we're not sitting there seeing the rest
But see, he
>> he's seeing the bills for everything other than
fuel,
electricity,
and heating oil. Okay. So he has all the details for that.
It's just that those three things
because I'm the one that signs the overall contract for fuel oil,
and all the electrical bills come in to me. So I see so I have that information.
That's the only reason why those two get handled separately,
because I see that globally for all the
but like normal bills, he's got as much information as I do.
>> Okay.
So so what would be
positive for us even in other departments is to understand the
current situation
plus or minus,
you know, that
all of these accounts are good, or we might have an account that is significantly underspent and we can sit there and decrease that line item because Jay's not really telling us that if he's got anything significantly underspent
and he's just asking for the same number as last year.
So, I mean, we need to look at those, Eric, and see those.
>> So, Jeff,
not that I'd be able to get it this done in time,
probably for you, but,
unless I spent the god amount of time doing it.
But
I in the spreadsheet,
I guess I could add a column that would show you what we're currently at. Like for for physicals,
we've currently spent three zero one dollars
Seminars,
we haven't spent any money yet.
Building maintenance,
we
spent $15,000
already.
Furnace I'm
>> expecting Jay all to be reasonable. It's just a question, you know, it's the outlier accounts more than anything. If
there's a significant under expenditure or there's a significant over expenditure,
then it makes sense as to why you're trying to increase something
to a given level, or, you know, do we have an opportunity to decrease in another area? And that's all I'm after. Yeah. I don't necessarily,
I mean, I would love for you to do that. I would love for every department to do it like this and have the detailed tabs behind it and then say, here's the details, because then we can walk through it. I mean, you're
Eric, what is Public Works?
Half of our total budget?
Maybe 40%?
>> I don't know the answer. It's probably close.
I would say 40%,
>> probably. 40%.
So in one night, Jay, we're going through 40% of the budget
and
understanding
that if we don't give money to you, then things don't happen.
So
roads don't get plowed, ride alongs don't happen, we don't move our roads, we don't do good things. So we have to fund what works.
The question is,
does every but every line item need to be funded at last year's number? Are there any potential areas where we can drop? Because
we're gonna have a big increase this year, and it's gonna be tough to push to the the
the town residents. So Right.
>> And, Jeff, if you look at the overall town budget spreadsheet
Yep. You'll see that I addressed
some of Jay's numbers either by
putting notes in the column or actually physically changing that,
because I also look through last year's completed profit and loss
Yeah.
You know, in compare, which is essentially not what was budgeted last year, but what we actually spent department by department in each line item. You know, you'll see a bunch of stuff in senior transportation,
where every year they budget for a certain amount. And every year I tell them they need to increase it because,
you know, they're spending way more than that. And they say, well, no, it should be the same budget as last year. So I've actually done that. And if you look at the overall budget document that you have,
you know, you'll see I put notes in there where we spent,
you know, money that was either over or under the previous year,
you know, and what I did. So the budget, the overall budget you see
is not exactly verbatim what you get from any department head.
>> No. You're already making adjustments based on where we're at. So, like, if I look at your budget, I look at public works, the total spend on that tab is $6.27.
And then I click down the line.
We had, snow removal $1.00 2. So now we're at 700,000.
Are there any other segments here that are related to Jay?
I I just don't wanna miss something. Is there something No.
>> Jay is basically True. Town garage,
public works facility,
snow removal budget,
>> and then the capital line item that relates to public works. Okay. So where, am I missing a tab for town garage?
I'm not. I don't think I am.
>> In the overall budget, it is $2.30
line and line $2.33
and on.
>> $2.33
and on. Oh, not in not in Jay's spreadsheet, in the overall In your spreadsheet.
Correct.
Okay.
Tell me, because I'm missing it. I can't see that tab because of the way you have it laid out.
Okay. It's it's So if I go through your tabs Row two thirty three.
So you're going into the
main budget, two thirty three. Correct. But
does that relate to a tab that you have downstream?
>> I don't think town garage
would necessarily
be a tab.
I'd have to look and see whether I made an independent tab for that.
>> No, I did not. Okay. So that's only
a $35,000
budget,
that section. Am I Town Garage?
I Correct.
Okay.
Is there anything else there that town garage,
public works
and snow removal?
And then the capital.
>> Yeah. And then we got the capital line items. Public works equipment fund.
Treaty.
>> Well, that's true. Tree maintenance. Tree removal should be
considered as part of your
purview. So
>> we set with building. You want me back out of this?
Or you got any?
>> Just slide up for me. Okay. Slowly
so I can look. Oh, sorry.
I actually I have yours open on my other screen. I I I had opened
it already.
Okay.
>> I had opened it. Where did I open it?
Oh, no. Did I?
>> I have too many things open, Jay.
That's
there it is.
Oh, it was part of Eric's big email.
So you are on the garage budget?
>> Yeah. Currently, I'm on the garage budget.
I had it at 37, $8.45,
and then
Eric decreased on the,
electricity side, which brought it down, almost
2,000.
So
>> Okay. So there's nothing there's nothing of
you've only had a couple line items here that you're asking for in excess of the prior year number. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Just
yep.
Okay. Is fire extinguishers
in here?
No.
No. Okay.
Alright.
Fire extinguishers
was in the
operating.
Right?
Yeah.
>> Okay. Which which one are you going to next, Jay? Alright. Thing that might change on this, just so that you're aware,
>> is I finally got updated contracts
from
fire protection services for the annual maintenance
and alarm,
you know, the monitoring contracts. I haven't even put those numbers in,
but we do have updated numbers. So I will probably adjust those values
when I've looked through and figure out what the contracts are actually going to cost us.
>> Jay, So without you having to open TreeWorks, TreeWorks $50,000
you're moving, you're asking for the same number. Yep, yep. And,
>> you know, we're doing pretty well there.
I try to get as
With several sources arm as much as I can to get some cooperative work. You know, obviously
we've got a lot, tremendous amount of tree work to be done.
We did quite a bit ourselves this year, raising canopies in different parts of town, which helped a lot
and thinning out some of the brush on our roadside edges.
So we're pecking away at it.
I'm
I'm okay. You know, if we can hold that $50,000
I mean, we always like to have more, but if we can hold that, that would be
helpful.
>> Alright. Did you have during any forums, did you have any problems?
With trees?
Yeah.
>> No. Nope. Just, can't can't get to them fast enough for everybody.
You know? We've got we've got a lot of what's that?
>> Because if Scott doesn't complain, no one's complaining. So, Scott, have you been complaining about the trees and the removes? I think that everything looks really good myself.
>> Okay.
I always look, Jeff.
Yeah, I know. Mean Dieter Mill's about
there's problems down there, but he knows about it.
>> Oh, yeah. I'm trying to get Eversource. Now that we're into the new year, they say they have some money, and they, now they're willing to talk.
You know, and actually just
quickly, I'll just make a couple minutes on cider mill. We need to do a lot of work there to get to take care of those trees. A lot of lot of trees need to be removed.
But I'm assuming because of the historic nature of that road,
you want to keep it
pretty much the same.
We should put up some start replacing some of those wood guide rails and, you know, leave them as wood guard rails. I'm assuming that's what you want in that area.
And you,
you know, just to preserve some of the historic value of that
area.
>> Jay, what's the cost per linear foot if we went to a timber backed guardrail?
Timber guardrail.
I know they're bloody expensive,
but how expensive is expensive?
>> I I don't know, Eric. I'd have to I couldn't I couldn't even say
at this moment.
>> I mean, Scott, Jeff Jeff Murray, because you've lived here, is Cider Mill really considered a historic road? I know it has the the the cemetery, but
>> the rest I would say so. They used to live on it.
>> Yeah. Mean, it's got the old mill and everything on it, so I don't know. It
>> has the
old mill on it. I've been on Cider Mill multiple times. There's an old mill. I mean, there's a little house down by the river.
>> There's only like three houses on it, four houses. The bridge going across, was a mill site right there behind
the,
the Tudor.
>> Right where they used to have the
ceremonies right next to the in that small area
next to the cemetery, they used to have the ceremonies.
>> I I don't think it's any more historic than any of the other roads we have in town.
Alright.
>> So if you wanna do guardrails, I wouldn't see a big issue with it.
>> Alright. Well, we can discuss that another time.
Alright. Let's move. Let's see. Capital
tree, we're all set.
We bring up.
Capital
equipment purchasing.
And I'm not sure
I have this on
or do I?
Hang on.
Did I put this on a spreadsheet?
Skid steer.
Nope. That's not the one I'm looking for.
Hang on.
Okay.
I got it.
Share.
Alright. Did it come up?
Yeah. Yep. Okay.
I'm getting better at this.
Yeah. Okay.
So
first line item is we have our
Freightliner plow truck coming in.
And I know it's 56,000
and change. I just rounded it up to 57.
>> It's actually 58,881
with tax.
Oh, okay. For not without tax, but with
with,
>> that's the invoice amount that we have for that. Okay. Sorry about that. 58 what was that again, Eric?
58881.
881.
Okay. Yep.
>> Alright. I have a question about the trailer, though, Jay. I thought that that was, you know, a $10,000
trailer.
>> Correct.
But we wanna put a new deck on it. Yep.
And
new springs on the ramps. So I increased
it by a few thousand dollars.
Whether we would spend all of that money, didn't. I don't know. It just depends on the price of lumber and miscellaneous
items.
Why we have the deck off,
you know, we can paint anything
in in the rails and whatnot
and clean things up.
So
this particular,
now that we're talking about this trailer,
So
this trailer is owned by Mark Williams.
We've looked at other trailers
and
some other trailers in this.
20 ton
price range, the webs underneath their cross members, you know, were rotten right out and weren't even worth looking at.
So.
This trailer is is available.
It's got newer tires and the brakes that were done
a couple of years ago, so we know that that's all up to date
and
it's bringing our
45 year old trailer up to a 2,004.
It's a little wider, it's a little longer,
better
suited for our needs.
Any questions on that?
>> No. Did we talk about this last year and just didn't do it?
Yes.
Okay.
Yep.
>> Thought this was, I thought this was already, that was already getting done the trailer. My, is it just got pushed over year to year or what what is the situation?
>> Well, we didn't get to do a few things that we wanted to to to,
fund it.
So we were hoping we could, fund it through other avenues and we weren't able to do it.
So we just put it off.
Commercial snowblower,
just
a simple,
It's a push, it's not a self propelled,
but it is a commercial. We have a
homeowner,
one now that's an older one. It works. It's a two cycle.
It'd be nice to keep that one as a spare,
but we do
use these.
They're convenient. They're not too hard to move around.
It'd be nice to have this for walkways
that we do currently do.
Town hall library
and
in front of our place to once in a while when we know it's not self propelled.
No, it's it's one of the it's it's a it's a commercial, you know, it's it's got the rubber the rubber paddles.
So it flips it right into the chute and spits it right out. And,
it it's not a heavy you know, it's not you're not gonna go out and do,
you know,
the whole sidewalk along the roadside with something like this. This is just you know, you gotta you're going from building to building, doing short sidewalks
that, you know, are
difficult to shovel.
Yeah. But she you know, as you get older and your back's not such good shape.
Right. I'm crying. Instead of shoveling.
>> Yes. Yeah.
So,
you know, to work with not doing so much shoveling, let's put it that way.
Alright.
So we talked about the Freightliner,
the jumping jack
compactor.
Our current compactor is twenty three years old.
We can't get it. We can't get parts for it. It needs a new carburetor.
It's just it's not running well anymore. It's hard to use. We need a new jumping jack.
Eric, you will appreciate this. We did look at the electric one,
but the electric one is is twice the money than some and for the amount of times that we use it. And to be honest, not
not so sure we want to have that big of a battery being stored on-site with some of the
things going on
out there. But anyway,
we did look into the electric one.
If we ever have to
do something
inside
anywhere,
definitely this would be the machine to have.
But this jump
and jacks four cycle
and
all other compactors
or whackers
from Able Tool.
Big ticket item this year is the John Deere roadside mower.
It's a
same size mower as what we currently have.
It would be a
four wheel drive. If we go with a two wheel drive, it only changes at about $2,000,
and it's longer to get.
We do have very rarely, but we do have the occasion where four wheel. Do we need it? No.
But
on occasion, it would be nice to have when we do get in those bad spots
and just availability wise,
like anything else, they're available. Others are not
as as so readily available.
It'd be a special order on a two wheel drive machine.
>> I looked that up, Jay. That's quite a quite a tractor.
>> Yes. It is. Yep. And this has a 22 foot boom instead of an 18 foot boom. Yep. What kind of mowers on it? It would have a
60 inch flail head.
We can use the same knives that we currently have, which we have cases and cases of knives.
And
the
With a with a new mower?
>> Oh, yeah. Everything brand new.
And we'd also have the ability to put this change the knives out to
the axe head, put axe head knives on when we're doing some
beatbacks where we get into the heavier brush.
So rather than behind the school?
Yes.
The stuff that's behind when we initially did that big stuff behind the school. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We could when we rented the machine.
Yes. We could do stuff like that. Yes.
Hopefully now with the stuff all beat back, we don't have to,
hopefully, we won't have to do that as long as we keep up with it. We won't have to rent again?
Correct.
>> The question becomes,
now I I just for number's sake, I inflated this a little bit by about,
5 to $8,000,
just because of timing and, you know, getting some final numbers
or some real good solid numbers.
The question becomes
how we finance this.
I was asked by Eric to provide you, and I apologize I didn't have time to do it, but an update on,
you know, a capital
equipment replacement
over a period of time, you know, so many years. And I know that we're
working towards replacing trucks every five to six years.
And then,
you know, having a just our spare truck go away as when a new one comes in.
But because of the cost of equipment.
From pandemic have skyrocketed so much, you know,
that we have to look at that differently. I
think, you know, we still can do the.
You know, the future outlook.
But I think you're we're looking at looking into a lease purchase for this machine as well. You know, these machines are not a $140,000
anymore.
$150,000.
They're they're big money.
And to get a small machine or a smaller machine
now we're instead of a commercial grade, you're looking at economical,
you know,
machines that
aren't really gonna,
stand up for the test of time.
So our our current machine
is 23 years old. That's a 2,001.
Still in pretty decent operating shape,
has some value.
If we were to
sell it,
you know, I hope hoping we would get somewhere between 20,000 or
plus. I don't know. That's kind of a hard number, but we don't have no idea where it would come in.
But that's a good starting number to
to market that machine.
Getting a little more difficult to get parts.
We've we've had to do extensive work, continue to do work on the boom.
We replace pins, you know, it's a they're high, high maintenance machines.
You know, they are what they are.
So any questions on that?
>> Eric, we have the Public Works Equipment Fund.
Yep.
And
last year we funded $101,100,000
dollars
$125,000.
How
much money is left after paying for the plot?
>> Not
much.
In
last year's
budget,
we overspent
the public works equipment budget
by about $40,000
or $35,000
to make the first lease payment,
which we've made.
This year,
I don't know where we're at
so far in expenditures
this year,
but I could find out.
Roughly half of this year's budget will be taken up in the payment
to
the cloud truck.
>> Okay.
I mean, that is in my mind where we need to start putting money away to allow Jay to pick and choose what he needs to do. I think we should probably put this on
a capital,
CIP,
put it on their table because that's what
we should do, and then
evaluate whether we can come up with the money or not come up with the money. But
if you don't get it, Jay, it means that you have to put more maintenance dollars into your current piece of equipment.
>> Yeah. We would just continue to maintain as we've been maintaining.
It's part of
It's equipment.
Just part of our maintenance budget
of
what do I got 17,
almost $18,000
requested
in maintenance,
equipment maintenance.
So that's where we fund, you know, a lot of time, you know, some some of that time is just felt spent
grinding and welding. You know, it's
part of our
budgetary dollars.
>> And
and
I'm assuming that's what the guys are doing now?
>> Yeah.
Yeah. We you know, if something
if something breaks down, we fix it. And it's all part of our gets incorporated into our maintenance. Okay. So you would Hopefully hopefully, we don't have any major things come up.
You would like hours are on that tractor?
>> Three
it's
not quite four thousand four thousand hours.
I'd have to go look at it, Scott. I know it's I know it's 3,000 and change.
>> Last time I Is there any is any programs like what that we did with the new power truck?
>> Yeah. There are. I just I don't have those numbers as far as,
lease purchase. I can get them.
I just did I didn't have time to get that before this meeting.
You know, like if it was $50,000
a year for the next four years or, you know,
spread over five years, I can get those number. I just didn't I didn't was able to get them before this meeting.
>> Right. And when I look at this, I look at not what we need this year,
but I look at
what your equipment requests are over a ten year period,
what the average cost of those pieces of equipment amortized over ten years, and I assign a number
to
the public works equipment fund for any given year.
You know, the object being to level out the funding year to year in all the departments so that there aren't any big spikes up or down.
We've obviously exceeded the Public Works Equipment Fund overall almost every year since I've been here in one form or another.
So, but
without seeing an actual ten year plan and understanding what the costs are,
I did not increase the amount
that I put in the overall
public works equipment fund.
>> K.
So
we need to get you and Jay together to come up with a ten year plan.
Okay.
Yeah.
>> I I I sit there and I look at what Scott is saying, even though I hate interest and I I don't I don't like it. I understand that it's it's
an easier way for the community to swallow the overall
annual expenditure.
So
if you can come up with that, then we can sit there and revisit
it. But we should also do what Eric is asking Jay and come up with a plan for the next ten years of
and and it and it's just gonna be when it happens. Here, there's a list of everything that we we should replace within the department,
and
here's the current costs, and it's gonna escalate the longer we wait. So.
Anybody have any questions on Lamar?
>> Right, but remember, we went from an original plan
of trying to modernize public works over fifteen years
to try to modernize
public works in five or six years.
That's really the difference.
You know, it's just a question of, is that budgetable?
>> That's
the point. Mean, we're not making a decision today whether that's budgetable.
We're listening, understanding what his request is. And then we just have to sit there and determine, okay, we either pass this to public works this CIP this year or we don't.
And isn't that what we're we're doing here?
Yep.
>> I I was asking Eric that one. I mean, that's Yep. Yep. Right? I mean, is
>> the tractor good enough, Jay, to put a new mower on it?
>> I
would say no, Scott.
I don't I don't know, you know, there's little nuances that are happening with the tractor, you know, sometimes it doesn't shift right or something, you know, just the the hydraulics,
the hydraulic motor,
you know, there's a lot of
screaming going on. That thing runs hot. It just,
it's getting time,
you know, and it's really something we need to put on
our
radars and figure out how we can replace it,
you know, when.
You know, fortunately, we haven't had any major
breakdowns
with the machine
since I've been here anyway.
Yeah, we've had some,
you know, where the boom needed to be repaired or, you know, you get some, like I said, some
welding needed to be done or when the mower head went down, we had a hard time getting parts.
You know, we do have a spare
set of bearings for it now. So if the bearing goes, you know, we can get them replaced. Hydro one,
you know, last time was a hydraulic motor.
The drive motor for the mower head Took a long time to find one. It just, you know, it just gets harder and harder to find
stuff to repair on these older machines.
Yep.
But when it's running, it's running.
So
K.
Alright.
Any other questions for anybody?
No?
>> Okay. Do you have any other segments you wanna go over, Jay? Yeah. The last one.
>> See if I can get this one up.
Capital roads.
So capital roads,
and forgive me because I don't have a spreadsheet for it, but I can for the new one. Do you have the email that I sent Eric?
I'll bring out the only what I can put up is my current
Capitol Road
spreadsheet.
Okay.
>> So do you have the email that I sent Eric on this with my notes?
I had it up.
So
>> Okay. I don't know where I put it now, but go ahead. I I I was looking at it before.
>> Alright. So keep in mind the way my
head works
as far as I'm
combining the totality
of Town Aid Road,
which is typically,
you know, dollars 180,000,
dollars 190,000
a year. We get a couple payments of
90,000 and change, right, Eric? 96,000,
something like that? Correct.
So
just for numbers sake, say it's $190,000
And then,
and then we have the town contribution
of
on
that.
For
road improvements.
So
last year,
I'm not sure I got all these numbers correct,
but last year
we got
$3.76,
Call it $377,000
from the town.
And then if you add in the
tar.
So that was my total money that I had last year. And if I go through,
and this spreadsheet,
this design, you know, layout,
patching, pavement, chip seal and drainage
is the same for my tar.
I tend to spend money out of tar before I come before I come
here
because tar tends to be
my startup money in the springtime
prior to getting the approval,
you know, the budget. So at least I can start the construction season ahead of time. I know we've talked about this a few times. So,
anyway,
so to my email,
bottom bottom of the email,
you know, I'm asking for $600,000.
So that's the totality between
what we would get from TAR and
what we would get from the town.
And then
I gave you the breakdown
of approximately
the the items that we try to accomplish
during the year.
Now, last year,
besides the preservation that we did
of the roads that we had list for chips sealed,
which we had, if you recall,
Wheeling, Pine Ridge, Shadlow,
Dogwood, Woodfern, Hutchinson, Times Farm, Old Coventry.
So
we ran into a little bit of a snafu last year of 100 and
Chip Seal was 152,000.
That didn't get done.
So currently, that 152,000
is
still in our budget
this year.
And
waiting to be spent if we approve to, have that,
chip seal done.
>> So for this year you get can you use that or can you get the chip sealing started in June?
>> Yes. So I have
the and that's something Eric and I've been discussing.
Are we going to use the same contractor or not?
And,
you know,
we'll we him and I are talking about that.
You didn't like that
contractor, did you? Well
>> no. I
gotta be honest with you. I like I like this contractor.
Are they sometimes difficult to work with?
You
know, it's not the first time. They they kinda piss me off. Oops. Sorry. They,
you know, I was a little upset with them last year.
But,
you know,
I still like the work they do.
Do things happen once in a while? It happens with everybody. I I don't know. But
they're telling me the June 1
to to have this work done to
complete this job, and they're holding the same price.
So
and that'll be a decision
that'll mean at another time, I guess.
So last year's budget,
due to reconcile reconciliation,
we had
some
over through the audit
process,
we had some over expenditures
and.
We overspent the budget.
So $80,000
came out of
the
capital improvement fund
to pay for the deficit in TAR.
So
which lessened the account
to 8, you know, the
capital account for this year, 80,000.
So I guess it was in retrospect, it was a good thing at the time the chip seal didn't get done.
>> In the meantime, he was put back in your house.
>> Yes. So
I still don't have all the you know,
I was told that I still have to reconcile these accounts.
So
I did put that money back in, you know, into the budget, made notes into my spreadsheet.
But,
so
my numbers
currently,
show
that we would have
right now 239,322
and change
in Town Aid,
not the Town Aid Road, in our Road Improvement Fund. If you back out the 152,000,
we spend it in June,
we would have a balance of starting,
the new fiscal year eighty eighty seven thousand and change,
to start the new year. And tar
would be showing a bet is, according
to my numbers, $500.
So,
that's what we would be starting with this year. Now I don't know. I think we received a new
par
since the last time. So, you know, that should be increased by
90,
if that's correct.
So those those should be the balances currently,
pretty close to it anyway,
because like I said, I don't have the exact numbers yet.
So that would help us get into
the start up of the season
last year because of
the budget
and the
the audit process. We shifted gears. We didn't get to do some of the things that we wanted to do, but we did some other things. We did a couple of catch basin repairs.
We did some road edge repairs on Lake Road. We did, you know, lots of tree work, in house stuff,
and
we just utilize utilize
some money elsewhere to do other things.
But long and short of it, the list that I have that I gave you in the email
is
really close
to what we spent this year. And I'm going to now I'm going to go back to this year's budget.
So without bringing in the TAR
money, and I'd have to I'd have to split the screen. I don't know if you want me to do that or not, but,
you know.
>> Well, this is the one spreadsheet I don't think we got.
>> Right.
But are you seeing this in the screen? Yeah. Right now?
Okay. So let's see if this works. Oh, I can do it. Alright. Hang on a second.
Tar. Can you get over to the left?
>> And then
k. Now I wanna bring this one in.
Is it gonna let me do it?
And bring this
okay.
Let's see. Let's this one.
Ah,
okay.
Alright. So you're looking at can you see the two my two spreadsheets?
No.
Oh.
You have to go back to
>> I gotta go back to the share button. Hang on. You gotta go no. You're in we've seen your primary one,
but you did something to your screens. You you need to show your full screen,
and
you need to split your screen.
>> But I don't think you can share from two different screens
even if you can see them on your screen.
>> Well, he can he he
he's probably on I don't know if he has two screens up, but you have to
drag the spreadsheet over to the edge of one of the screens.
>> Right. That's what I just did, but I thought it alright. Oh, let me
let me hang on.
Let me back them away and see what we gotta do here
because I probably didn't share it when I was supposed to.
>> Yeah. We're still looking at you. You're still doing it, but this
spreadsheet is probably covering up the other spreadsheet. So Okay. So which spreadsheet
are you seeing?
>> Right. It's the 2023,
twenty twenty four Capital Road budget.
>> Okay. 202324
Road budget. You're seeing that?
Correct.
Okay.
Alright.
Let me bring up the other screen.
>> No. I don't
Jay, you have to do everything on one screen because you're only sharing one screen.
Hang on.
Sorry.
>> It's alright. So if on your screen, you you split the files?
Yeah. I was trying to bring put up two two spreadsheets on one screen. And you should be, you should be able to do that. And then you share that screen.
Oh, is that what it is? Yeah. You can't have them on two different screens. You gotta have them on one screen. Yeah.
>> I still don't think you can share
because your screen is still two screens
just side beside,
but I don't know.
I've never tried that.
>> As long as it's showing on your desktop, on your screen,
and you share your desk and you share your desktop that way.
Yeah. It'll show it.
Yeah.
>> Alright. What do you got right now? Just one spreadsheet.
The twenty three twenty four capital tar? Yeah.
>> Road. Oh, no. No. Road road budget. Capital road budget.
This one's different. This one has Target, Kuwait.
>> Correct. That's that's this year's. I was trying to
anyway,
it's not working for me. We'll go through the technical lessons. Paula will Yeah. I guess up there could be another lesson later.
Let's get to our numbers.
Road budget.
So in the
All right. So you're seeing here's my spreadsheet,
the summary page.
We're on that.
All right. So in capital
improvements and capital tar,
Initially,
beginning of the season, I start using tar monies
and I got the tar in my previous screen. So I mean, my other screen. So I'm going to just tell you what I spent.
So
in paving and shimming,
you know, through the subcontractor
we use
and expensive
asphalt
in the tar side, I spent $121,000
And then
I picked up the balance of that
in the road improvement fund
of an additional $17,000
Okay,
so
that's what we just that's what we spent last year between the two
for
paving.
Now chip ceiling.
Last year,
now we didn't do initially,
we had budgeted for $230,000
you see on the bottom and ended up because of through adjusting what roads we were going to do, ended up being $152
because we're going to do some drainage on some of those roads that we initially wanted to do last year,
which we didn't do.
And.
>> Well, we did the crack seal,
which was 39 and change,
which I have this year,
40,000.
If you look on the
list that I gave you in the email.
So I'm still budgeting. I'm still asking for $40,000
in crack seal.
I'm still asking for approximately
$200,000
to 25 per chip seal,
give or take, depending on the roads that we do or what we're, you know, what we decide to do.
Haven't locked down that list yet. We do know that we want to do last year's
chip seal roads, but we want to do some road improvements
up towards if we can
burnout Brook area, get up into that end of town.
So the asphalt,
getting back to asphalt again,
$95
a ton is still holding, give or take a dollar or 2.
So
I try to budget for a thousand ton
at and $95,000.
And the contractor,
we
budget for twenty two days at $4,450
per day.
Last year
hang on.
Last year, it was I think it was it was $4,002.50.
So he's a couple $100 more a day than he was last year.
Catch basins
to our list.
Stock replacement,
I had asked for 14,800
last year,
and pipe
14,250.
This year,
I'm asking for 30,500
for stock replacement.
Catch basin cleaning
20,000
that last year we did.
Hang on.
I think I did that in
where did I do the catch basin cleaning?
We had,
Shaw's back services last year was 18,936.
We spent
for Shaw's
catch basin cleaning.
And not only are we doing catch basin cleaning,
we try to do inlets and outlets of all the cross culverts and any pipes that we can get to from the edge of the road.
So any exposed pipes
that way, hopefully the natural course of,
you know, water running through these pipes, they tend to flush themselves out.
So we try to maintain the
the ins and outs of those pipes as well and
get them cleaned.
So I include that in the
number of catch basins.
So,
roadbed material,
$15,000
I'm asking for.
Flex beam and guardrail.
So this year
>> think I know where's Jay my Jay, do have
a summary of what your plan I mean, I know you're asking for these numbers, but do you have a list of the roadways you're planning on doing?
For this for this year, I don't have a For every for every year. I mean, it's like the ten year plan. What what are you looking at doing? And then these roads
become the priority that you're planning on working on.
Mean, just so we as a group understand, okay, this is
this is what what should get worked on in the next in the coming season. It may not. Like, there might be items that are down at the bottom you might not get to, but that would be helpful.
>> So this this year,
the roads we would like to complete the chip seal roads, we know that,
and we had plans on the drainage to start
Skinner,
Long Hill
through Hendi and
and then the drainage on Hendi
going down to Pine Ridge.
We want to start that project.
Last year, we didn't we weren't able to.
And that's what we would like to do this year.
As far as
preservation
for to
do chip seal roads, we want to start in on Burnout,
that area.
We have some problem spots
that we need to address.
And to have an exact list for you,
I don't, other than to complete what we finished last year or what we wanted to start last year in chip seal roads and start on our drainage.
We have that water issue on aspenal that we need to do.
That's going to be just tearing up the road and see if we can take care of getting that water down to the catch basin
where the water,
the spring in the middle of the road, and I'm not sure if you are all aware of that, so that needs to be done.
Kinda still in,
fire
mode.
I I
I don't have a list, an exact list for you right now.
>> Alright. That would be helpful. So, like, we we look at these dollars and go, okay. This is where the the resident's taxes are gonna go, and this is the plan you got working forward for the schedule of roads.
>> Yeah.
I mean, it's like the the
flex beam and guardrail.
We'd like to continue replacing the guardrail on Long Hill. That's all contractual.
Last year, we did
1,300
just over 1,300 feet.
And it was $36,965
from Atlas Vets.
And
we have all of that and then some left to do on Long Hill. We're gonna be getting rid of those
That rope rail would rope rope rail.
So it's a continue, you know, these things are continuations
of
other work.
It's what we've been spending.
Road markings and striping,
same same money.
And the roads, you know, the road signage I asked to increase to $8,000.
We haven't really had any money for road signage. I've been just
taking a little bit from here and there.
So that was a
an increase there.
But these items that I've listed are
base basically what we've been spending the last
four years since I've been here.
You know, they've been altered a little bit
depending on what we've,
adjusted as we go along.
They haven't really changed.
Okay. So
>> does anyone have That doesn't really answer your question. So
I don't I don't have a list a specific list
of
roads. It's just the amount of money and keep applying them to what we have
continuing long held to flex beam, continuing
roadside preservation move into,
you know, we would have we may have to adjust those dollars where we don't get to do as much chip seal,
because we gotta take care of Aspinall,
because that's been a that's still a problem. We really should get over get over there and do that.
>> Well, what what I'm asking,
well, you
know,
it's it's like the list of all of the roads. And then if we have the list of all the roads and we know that we chip sealed Lake Road ten years ago, Lake Road can last another five years, but you have your cycle. So you just, you continue to put up that list and go, here's the cycle, this is where I'm at. I can't guarantee you I'm going to get to it in exactly the order that it's presented, but at least we all know
that this is the cycle.
Yeah.
>> So June, you're starting with the chip sale with Gorman.
Not if I can help the
And then and then road and what road are you gonna be going onto next? When are gonna do a hospital?
I think what Jeff's looking for is a,
you know, some kind of timeline.
But you gave it to us last year, remember.
And what, what you're gonna be doing when,
and,
then we can tell better what money you're going to be spending.
>> Well, it's, I
mean, the way I look at it, Scott, is like here's the list and it's going to all get done. It may not get done in the next fiscal year. It may get done the following fiscal year. May get done five years from now. Right. At least we all,
you know, like, I don't want,
I would rather the community understand
where public works is prioritizing
the roads and what their expectations are. Like,
Jay's out there all the time and his guys are out there all the time. I mean, I know we have two
you know, local guys on our board that understand the roads and know what the heck's going on and can come back and say,
these are the right roads to spend the money on.
That's all I'm after. I'm just after more of a,
hey, I could come to you, Jay, and if we sat there and said we're going to spend $600,000
every year, you're going to come to us next year and say, here are the roads that we're going to spend this on, and if you want me to spend it on, you want me to do more roads, I need an extra $100,000.
You might not get it from us, but at least we would understand where it potentially would go. Yeah.
>> Part of the problem is that you don't know where that grant is, right, for MD.
Correct. That is the problem.
We
>> know we know we have to do the drainage,
you know, and we'll patch as we go along.
But,
you know,
Ridge Road is another big problem. We got to address Ridge Road.
You know, the beginning of burnout
Ridge Road is a drainage issue there. We got to take care of that road,
you know, and there's some smaller roads that are busting up here and there. But we're trying to
trying to make the circuit,
you
know,
round robin some some sort of
process where we're kind of going in order around the town. And
I
don't know, got to find it. I know I've got a
spreadsheet
that, you know, we can keep up with the dates and when the roads were.
Well, we have our that other system too. But,
you know, when things were done and when we'd look to the life expectancy of these roads.
How long is Aspenol gonna take to fix?
>> Depends on what we find, Scott.
You know? Could be
it depends on what we have for ledge, how deep I can go so we can get some,
some underdrain underneath the road without
it affecting
the frost heave of the way things move during the winter. You know, if we can get low enough where we can draw that water off and
get some under drain
in there
without changing the whole
whole road. You know, we got we got half a lane we got to go up at least partway,
you know, at least a little bit beyond that house where the second house on the left, they're going up the hill.
So
we got a little bit of work there.
Less than a month, I would hope.
I mean, it should only take a few days to dig that dig that thing out, box it out, see what we got ledge,
I don't know, two, three weeks. It's hard to say until you get into it.
You never know what you're gonna find.
>> Okay.
Does anyone have any questions for Jay specifically
on any of his
requests?
Okay. Jay,
what we'll end up doing is, like I had said earlier, I
would like the summary of
your expectation,
especially by road. I think we should have a list of all of the roads
and
a corresponding date to the last time something was done on that road of of significance.
And, you
know, even culverts or even things that you're working on here, the potential problems, they might not be worked on this year. They might be worked on five years from now, but at least we see it.
But for this year's budget, we're gonna have to sit there and take your numbers and then look at them in totality of the whole budget.
While So I personally don't have really a lot of issues with what you're asking for because they're similar to the prior years, you're not asking for anything
crazy,
you know, that's a new project,
but we're gonna have to take this into totality with the rest of the town, and we might have to make some adjustments.
Understood.
We'll come back to you on that.
Okay.
>> Alright. Eric, is there anything we should be thinking about related to his budget
that you want to talk about now while we have Jay on the phone?
>> Yeah. So,
so my concern is, I'm still quite pissed that we don't know whether we're getting or not, because they haven't announced
who they're giving the grants to for the trip program.
If
we get the trip program and we're funded in this budget cycle,
then we desperately need to get the,
you know, we need to get the drainage done for that project
because we have, you know, we'll have money to pay for the actual road surfacing.
And at the same time, we ought to start talking about
how and what we do to reconfigure
the intersection
of Hendy
and Long Hill,
because that intersection's
been,
you know,
been a problem for a while, and the perfect time to tear that thing up is when you're tearing it up anyway and reconfiguring
it.
So, but we just, we flat out don't know.
Personally,
I think Gorman has kind of screwed us two years in a row.
I
personally wouldn't go back to them.
I would switch to Comer or a different chip sealing contractor,
You know, but that's just, that's me.
>> Who did the, which chip sealing company did the work on Lakeside?
That was probably four years ago.
>> Four years ago, Lakeside
was not ship sealed. That was That was Cape Sealed. Sealed. Yeah. Who did that?
That was
Indus did the Cape Seal part. Company called Comer did the initial
chip seal.
Okay.
>> And if you're not happy with them,
why would we continue? Do we have a contract with them for a timeframe?
No. We don't have any contracts with them.
>> Jay, are you
you seemed like you were happy with them, or is that not true?
>> I'm not happy with what occurred.
I'm happy with them in general.
I like the work that they do.
I'm not
opposed to having somebody else do it. It just there's things that
they do that other people that other companies don't. They're all they're all different. Their process is a little bit different. I wasn't happy with the the previous year. They had a lot of dust in the in the product.
It happens.
Could
it happen again?
Maybe someday. I don't know.
And it could happen with other people too.
It's stone
not necessarily the contractor.
>> Correct.
It's the type of stone you use. It's where they get it from. Was it washed properly?
Was it two, three times washed or did they only wash it once?
Apparently,
when we got the desk
last time, it
screened enough, wasn't washed enough.
And then just
the timing of them getting in last year.
Yeah. So it was a problem. Wasn't happy about it.
>> So what was their
reasoning? Are they gonna fix that this year or did they reply?
>> Did anybody talk to them about that? Oh, yeah, I talked to them about it. So last year they had some huge contracts in their home state of New York and they pulled all their crews over there.
So they didn't come back till
too late in the season and I wasn't going to have it done
at the end of the year when it was too cold and not have a good product.
So
I said
ship them on. We almost had them do it, but because I wanted to get done,
Well, we didn't. So
that's where we're at. Okay.
So with
without
>> having us to get involved, you and Eric are gonna battle this out and you're gonna be the right contractor. I'll side with Eric on this one. I do not wanna see the dust bowl we saw the year before.
It was it was awful. And a lot of residents couldn't even open their windows on a long hill. The dust was so bad.
It was terrible. You couldn't even see on the road. It looked like, you know, even with cars in front of you driving, you couldn't even see on the road.
And that went on for months.
So
definitely not.
>> I saw that Coventry had done chip sealing on, I think it was
Silver Street, Silver Lane, whichever it is, last summer. That looked like a good job. I don't know what company.
If you can find out who Coventry used,
it's any better.
>> So that was also a different,
somewhat different material and a much more expensive product.
That was a rubberized chip with
coated stone.
It does come out great
and there's very little dust, but it's also
almost twice the cost of what we do. Either you double the money or you half the number of lane miles if you do it that way.
I see. Okay.
>> Yeah, if they can guarantee that they can keep the dust down, I wouldn't have a problem using them again, but
I don't want to put any of the residents through what they went through a couple years ago.
I heard a lot of personal complaints from neighbors on Long Hill.
>> I
mean,
Jay's point, though,
every time we chip seal,
we get complaints.
>> Yeah.
That that wasn't dust. This this this was just bad. I mean, there was Yes. Just
>> I don't disagree. I drove that every day.
It was really annoying to a lot of people.
You're not going to get zero complaints
regardless of who you do.
There's always going to be some dust involved with the process. That was just a particularly
badly dusty year, and I agree with that, and I was very unhappy with it personally.
>> And our sweeper broke down and we couldn't get out to sweep in time. And so it sat there a lot much longer than it was supposed to.
>> And I feel like it was a dry it was a dry year environmentally.
>> So it was it was the perfect storm. Yeah. But we did get a lot of rain and it just never seemed to get the wash the dirt out of the stone. It just stayed in it. And then like every time it dried out again,
the dust bowl started again.
Yep. It took a long time. Don't disagree.
>> Okay. So
Jeff Murray has voted for against Gorman,
and the rest of us just don't want any dust, I'm assuming. So, Eric, you and Jay battle it out and figure out what you're gonna do for the money and
>> make sure there's no dust. We will hold you accountable. Unless you unless you change the process, we're not gonna be without dust. Understood.
>> Yes. You I understand we're gonna have some dust, but not excessively like we had two years ago.
>> Alright. And they assured me that that wouldn't happen like that again. But I
yeah.
>> Is there anything in in,
is there anything in the contract or an addendum
to say if it happens again, they're gonna give us a credit or I don't know.
Is there any way to hold them accountable for that?
Yeah. Choose a different vendor.
>> All right. Let's not harp on this. Let's move on. Okay. You guys, you're gonna do a great job to fix it. We'll move on. Battle it out. All right. Any, specific anything else, Eric, besides those issues
that you wanna address while Jay's on the line?
>> No. The other thing I don't know how it's going to shake out because I don't know how much the
the
school
actually has
to spend on the upper parking lot.
I mean, they still are adamant that they want to reclaim and repave the upper parking lot, but we don't have a dollar figure about how much they're actually going to contribute.
And then the question becomes, do we do it anyway?
And if so,
where do we take the excess funds to do that?
>> So that's an open question, and I just, I don't have an answer to that. Well, we need to talk to the Board of Education and sit there and understand because
they were,
I mean, they had extra funding that basically what you're saying is
the auditor doesn't believe that their number that they thought they were gonna have extra is there anymore.
>> That is correct. So they spent the money that was in the
for that check?
Or the check was no good to start with? What happened there?
Would it it's, not
>> the conversation. That that's, I mean And I don't I don't have because they share no financial data with the town, I have zero insight into what they have budgeted or what they've expended.
>> Okay. Alright. So all things that we need to to deal with. And
if the
Board of Education wants that done,
as discussed previously,
they had the additional
funding to assist
in the majority of the cost of that. So we'll work back toward that,
and we will get through the issues. But I would assume if they
they must have had a problem with the auditor. So we'll sit there and we have to get and I'm I know what you're gonna say, Eric. I know you don't have the details related, but that would be the
that would be as an accountant, my guess is they had a problem with the auditor, or they would be here talking
to Eric about doing it
and
saying they had all the funding they needed. So, okay, we'll deal with that one down the road. That's not
that's a capital improvement item.
It needs to go to CIP. It needs to get addressed
regardless of whatever agreement we come to with the Board of Education,
it'll get put in line.
We'll
>> deal with that after the fact.
Sure. Anything else for Jay?
>> No. I think the only other question we've got to decide is
whether it's worth it to renew our contract with with street scam,
you know,
and whether we want to get the roads rescanned.
What value has it given you guys?
Well,
>> I'm not
directly doing the roadwork or accounting for it. So it's it's not that's a Jay question, not an Eric question.
>> Okay, Jay. I to be honest with you, I haven't had time to use it,
You know, with with taking care of what's the business side of this
facility
and working with the guys and filling in,
you know, and doing the work beside them, I just haven't had time
and
I haven't been able to use that system. And I actually the time that I have spent,
I've found it difficult to use.
We had some hiccups
with it and they did some upgrades.
Just I haven't had been able to spend any time with it. Oh, do you wanna renew it?
How much is it to renew it?
1,800,
I think. Right.
>> No. I thought it was more than that.
Because I don't know. What what is the price to renew that, Eric?
>> I don't know. I sent it to you. I can look it up again.
I'd have to look.
>> Hang on. Well, the what what you're just telling me is I don't care what the cost to renew it is unless we have a person that's capable of utilizing effectively.
It's a waste of money. Right.
So whether it's Jay or not Jay,
you know
Yeah. If it's not getting used
Don't renew it. Right. Just wasting money.
>> I mean, the the question comes down to do you wanna have an objective third party review of our road network periodically or not? If you don't, then street scans are waste of time. Well, You know, that's today's not using the rest of the functionality. Yep. Was it value, was it valuable and was it accurate? I felt like sometimes,
>> unless I'm wrong,
it wasn't always accurate or am I wrong?
>> Was it perfect?
No.
Did it reasonably reflect the overall quality of our roads? Yes.
Were there a couple roads they evaluated that said, don't think you
that makes sense? And did they have to go back and reevaluate?
Yes.
But
I mean,
>> I don't know. Get us get us get us the costs and and we'll we'll take that into consideration. That might be one item,
>> Paula, that we can cut because Yep. Street street can Street scan is $1,800.
Scott.
Nailing that. Damn dunk, Scott.
>> Yeah. That's just for the annual fee to allow the usage of their software.
Correct. Get them to rescan
the town and give us an actual updated evaluation,
which normally
for roadwork
management,
you figure on roughly every fourth
or fifth year
going to an outside vendor to make sure that what you're saying you're doing, you're actually doing.
That total cost
would add about 10,000,
you know, basically every fifth year or fourth year, if you choose to do it. If not, then we drop it. I think we should just let Jay decide.
He scans the roads every day.
>> Yeah. What's the pitfall on not having it? If Jay's,
>> you know I mean, know, let so
here's here's what I know about StreetScan.
And I've I've been, you know,
looked at it through previous jobs
or previous employment.
It does serve a purpose.
It all depends on your
your road maintenance program.
You know, if the if the town as a whole, I mean, obviously.
The town went to street scan because people needed to know what their roads were really like, because a lot of people spend the only roads they ever see is the roads when they get up in the morning and they leave to go to work and the ones that they come home on. They don't see the rest of the town,
so they don't know what the rest of the their road may be perfect.
And but everybody's screaming about somebody else's road or their road so bad.
So.
The the street scan in that process gave you an overall view of what your town and people people were able to see that.
So that's a that's a good good thing.
The,
the maintenance of that
and keep, you know, for me to sit here and and put all the documents takes up time. I frankly, I don't have it. I have enough just sitting here doing all this and then working with the guys and fill, you know, working with that. I got enough on my plate.
And
when I came here, there's a lot of busted up stuff all over the place and and.
You know, we did. We switched to a better,
what I like to think, better preservation program
and did things a little differently and we can get around.
Now, is that the end all end all? It is not because the town as a whole has got to start banking some money because these roads that we preserve now,
you know, you may do,
you know, every five to seven years, you got to go back and hit the road you did.
So either you're doing another chip seal and on it, crack sealant in between.
But at some point you're going to look to do reconstruction.
So that's when you got to start incorporating reconstruction
costs.
So we kind of hit that a year ago where we did some
road preservation and we did some reconstruction.
You know, that reconstruction is big dollars.
And we're talking hopefully if that grant comes in, we'll do another section of town. But you have 35 miles of roads you're going to you know, you have to cover.
So
that that's a whole nother process that you got to incorporate
and
start sinking some some dollars into your
infrastructure.
>> Well, I mean Maybe you don't do We were, we were on street scans. I mean, we've already talked about,
about our
preservation program, Jay, right? So, you know, if we're going to talk about reconstruction and the total dollars of reconstructing,
it's kind of what I always
talk to Eric about is
have the entire plan, lay it all out and say, it's gonna cost you $25,000,000
to repave all the roads in town, just so people have an understanding of
when we ask for an extra $400.500000,
we're doing it with a logical reason to do it. Yeah.
>> That's why you use street scan to produce that data, if that's what you want.
And I agree. And but the difference is I think Jay is the guy that's gotta be putting the information in, not me, because it used to be me.
And, you know, it's not me making the roadwork decisions,
so it shouldn't be me dealing with the software.
>> Okay. So,
I would sit there and say that if we're going to get the software, then we have to figure out how to get Jay some assistance to get the software utilized.
Because if you're not utilizing the software, there's no reason for the software.
It
just sits there for four years and you're paying $1,800
a year to just keep something sitting there on your computer and not utilizing it. So really what we're at is we just
are all in a situation where Jay is probably not having enough time and,
you know, technologically,
he needs some assistance to sit there and manage that.
So
let's talk about it and sit there and see what makes sense.
But
I don't necessarily know I need a software
to tell me I have 35 miles of roads, and here are the names of the roads, and this is when they were last worked on. And if we chose to to to,
you know, reclaim and repave each road, this is what it would cost today and just use a
static
per
mile or per
foot rate.
And then we can at least just have a ballpark. That's a small spreadsheet,
>> you know. I mean, I'll give you that ballpark today. If you wanna reclaim all the roads of town, it's about 18,000,000
plus or minus, not including drainage,
>> not including anything else. And those are the things that we have to put in. Okay, there's drainage. I mean, you know, it's like that. And Eric, to me, I
would show that all to the community at the budget meetings and go, this is what it would cost. We don't have it, but this is why we're doing X.
Eric
and Jay have done a great job
maintaining the roads to the level they're currently at. And everybody's got to be aware. It's like the trees. It's,
you know, we spend $50,000
a year on trees,
but you had more trees fall on the trail during an event than you had fallen all 35 miles of roads into. Wow. That was very good.
And, but that's, that's
>> what the community needs to understand.
Right. What we're doing and why we're spending this money. Now,
we may not be able to
get everything we want, but
that's
just my opinion. That's something that I believe that the people need to understand.
It's,
you know, it's like their own house. You have to maintain your house or it falls apart around you. If you maintain what you have,
then it doesn't fall apart around you. If you if you just sit there and ignore it, it falls apart around you, and then you end up with bigger bills. And
what we've been trying to do is put money in the bank. It's not enough, Jay, I get it. I would tell you, I understand totally, but we don't have,
you know, a revenue base other than grants, which Eric, you've been doing a pretty good job on, but you got to do better. And, you know,
residents tax taxpayers. And so, and Eric, you're a taxpayer as well, so we all sit there and have to pay into the fund.
And to be really honest, it's a lot better than it used to be. But
we have to explain to them it's still, if we did this, it would cost us $20,000,000 We can't do that. We can't spend an extra million dollars, but
we can spend 600 or $700,000
a year and do a reasonably good job
until
we have a catastrophic
rain event and it washes our roads away.
>> Right. But, I mean, that is the whole point of of street scan,
to be able to logically
show the public
where you're at, what the overall road conditions are, and to be able to do it graphically year after year, and then every five years or so,
do an objective, this is what I've told you, you've increased the road quality by doing X, Y, and Z, and then have a periodic
independent inspection that comes in and says,
you really did it or you really didn't. Here's what you have. You know, that's what street scan is. You know, it's just a question of the,
Jay is right.
I mean, it took me an enormous amount of time initially to get it set up,
you know, and to work with it and to generate that data.
You know, and he's right, neither of us frankly have the time to do it correctly, but
so,
you know, and I recognize
that you've asked me for that data multiple times, but again,
kind of putting that all on paper and giving you,
you know, that that's an enormous amount of work.
You know, I can do it, but what else aren't we doing if we're doing that?
So that's really the question.
>> It's $460,000
a year
to do one mile. I mean, so if we put away $460,000
to redo,
restructure
a whole road every year, in addition to what he does now, we could do one
mile
every year. So it would take us thirty five years to get the entire Exactly. So we need And we'd have roads that are failing because they're 35. Well, they'd be done. I mean, a lot of the roads probably were done thirty five years ago. Yeah.
We need to double what we give Jay
to do this correctly.
>> Okay. And you and I both know or should know that we're never gonna get that much
from the community,
but we have to explain to them why we're asking for what we're asking.
So, I mean, all I'm sitting
there, I like exactly what you did, Scott. I would put it on one slide. It's $458,000
a mile.
We have 35 miles. You know, we need 17 or $18,000,000.
Five years. And
The thirty five year plan.
>> Yeah. It's a thirty five year plan. But we're not what Eric and Jay have been doing is not doing
every mile
because you're chip sealing and you're preserving the road. I mean,
is the Lake Road the best road I've ever driven on? No, but is it a good road? Yeah, it's fine. Yeah, yeah, it's fine. Biggest complaints for
everything that you, I think that you get is that people complain because the road's not flat and it hurts their dog's
feet, or they don't like to ride their bikes on it. Those are the complaints you get from chip sealing.
>> I mean, are there any other complaints from chip sealing other than dust? I mean We we we need need to, maybe we need to do, four quarter mile places
every year
or two half. We
need to redo some of these roads completely
every year.
>> Well, makes no sense to split them because you're mobilizing equipment, you're mobilizing people, you wanna get it done quickly and for the most cost effective. Have to make up the decision just like we did with the trees.
>> Right. The problem comes in with a limited budget.
You know, until you've shim and chip sealed the entire town at least once through,
your priority still has to be basic preservation
and increase the drivability of the roads. And Jay has done a fantastic job of that.
But we all know once we get through that round,
we're going to have to start switching
a fraction of the funds over
to
classical reclamation.
And it's really, it's more than just reclamation.
You should be looking at all the potential
techniques from cold in place recycling,
the hot in place recycling,
you know, because every road doesn't necessarily need exactly the same treatment.
And reclaiming
something like
Cider Mill Road
is probably a waste of money. Reclaim
you know, your trunk roads and your highest through traffic roads
and use lesser quality improvements on your less, you know, populated roads.
But, you know, sooner or later, you gotta you gotta address everything.
>> Yeah. We
we need a new line item and put away every money money just like we did for the bridges.
>> But the bridges but
the bridges, we got we got grants. And now we got we got them for free. That's what we got to
do across everything. We got to sit there and target grants and target opportunities to utilize money for,
like, what we're planning on doing in Endy.
And we have to do it, you know,
I'm sitting there looking at it, Scott, we have to justify to the community why we want $600,000
more
total dollars. I mean,
this is the biggest impact. This is what gets done and people drive on.
I mean, there's only two things in this community. It's roads and the transfer station. So you've done a pretty good job improving the transfer station.
People pay a little bit of money for it, that's fine, but
it's roads.
And our buildings have been looking better.
And Jay have done a great job with that. They have everything looks good. Let's not forget the cleaning guy because I love that man. He does a great job.
Billy is awesome.
>> He is. My, that building looks great. My cleaning guy does a great job down here too.
>> Yeah. You do a good job, Bert. Yeah. Good job. Excellent. I love it.
You know, the time you're cleaning, can be spending, like, using street smarts.
>> Well, yeah. Right. Yeah. But no, you go But then the crew is doing something else. I'm glad to get out of this seat for an hour.
>> All right.
Anything else for Jay?
Because, I mean, globally, we just all have to understand that what Eric is presenting us is an increase in total spending, so we're going to have to come back and evaluate what's
the threshold that we're willing to put toward the community.
And
if
>> we get to a point that we need to cut, we need to figure out where we're cutting.
>> Jay, thank you, Thank you, Jay. Appreciate it. Thank you. Appreciate your time. Yep, thanks for putting up with me.
>> No problem. Just give me my list, will you, please? Have a good I tried to get you some more money. Nobody wants to buy into it.
>> No. We all do the best we can. Have a good night. Yep. Thanks. Night, Jay. Alright.
>> So does anybody have anything else they wanna discuss,
related to what we've got going on? What's,
when, when
is, the town planner available, Eric?
>> Is that next week's? So the town planner will be on the regular scheduled meeting,
which I think is the thirteenth.
Okay. Yep.
>> Yep.
He's penciled in for that. So that will be, you can have the discussion
regarding
affordable housing.
You know, he's prepared to talk to that at length about, you know, what your, what your goals are and what can be done in terms of affordable housing.
>> So what are we gonna talk about next
budget
meeting?
What's up?
Well, what would you like to talk about at the next budget meeting? I don't know. I think we need to decide tonight so that we're
prepared
and efficient.
>> One thing I think we should probably talk about at some point is what's coming down the pike for the transfer station,
because I think we should probably be aware of that. It's not huge dollars,
but we're definitely going up a fair bit
at the transfer station
if we get into a new contract,
as we get into a new contract, because our contract is up as of July 1.
Now, some things in that are not fully
negotiated
yet
because we're,
for those of you who do or do not know, the town of Andover is part of Midnirach,
which is the Mid Northeast Recycling Consortium,
which is 13 towns
that all go in together to have increased buying power
for bidding
on a lot of the things that go on at the transfer station,
as well as runs
>> a hazardous waste
facility in Willington, where Andover residents can bring
their hazardous waste to be properly disposed of, because we don't have that capability
in hand.
So most of the contracts for that for the upcoming year have been settled at this point.
You know, we've been meeting for that all through the fall.
There are a couple,
they have asked
Casella
to come back in because they're, you know, as a group, we're not particularly happy with some of the aspects of
what Casella
is charging the members towns in terms of hauling fees
and the cost of recycling.
And they've added a new kind of slush fund fee
on top of all their other fees.
So
I would be happy to
give you the proposed contract
and an Excel spreadsheet that talks about the budget costs.
And I think then we also need to be starting that conversation with do we keep dues
the same, or do we keep dues, or do we increase dues for the transfer station?
So that would be one subject.
And then other than that, you tell me what it is you want to see and talk about the budget next.
What's Casella called the slush fund?
You want the name of the fund?
Yeah. What what do they call it?
>> I'll tell you in a second.
The energy and environmental
fee.
That
>> would be a floating fee that they determine based on some arbitrary
formulas, which they haven't shared with anybody,
and they apply to the total bill. So you have your contract,
and you itemize and you get billed what you get billed for the month, and then you add x number of percent, which they won't guarantee
on top of that, and bill that to you as their energy and environmental fee, which is supposed to make up for all the things that,
I don't know, they haven't already charged you for. But
there are a couple of things going up. The compactor lease fee
has gone up a lot.
Tipping fees are
going up a pretty modest increase, so I'm not too worried about that. The thing that is really going to hammer us is
the
cost for recycling.
The recycling costs are going up,
oh, somewhere around fourfold compared to what we're paying now per ton.
So that's going to be a big bite.
I mean, we're obviously not the only person,
you know, in,
you know, when I look at when,
you know, we've we've talked about that at the COG or Capital Region Council of Governments,
and I've looked at other areas outside of Mid Near that are with other suppliers,
our fees are actually pretty cheap compared to what they're proposing,
but it's still a big jump for us.
You know?
So bulky waste is staying
roughly the same. It's going up a little bit. That's still being trucked
shipped via rail card at the same facility in Ohio,
that it gets landfilled in Ohio.
We're still using the trash to energy plant, I want to say it's Montville,
for burning the garbage.
You know, but the recycling costs are what's really driving that.
You know, I'm trying to do some structural changes
by dedicating a cardboard only dumpster,
you know, which
that helps.
But and so get that out of the weight of the revenue. We
have room at the transfer station.
You know, we wouldn't save enough money. I mean, the ideal way to do it would be to put in a separate cardboard compact.
But given that we're going to pay $8 a year to rent a compact or I don't want to pay to rent another compactor just to we wouldn't recoup our money.
But
putting it in an open container
does seem to be cost effective versus putting it all
you know, in the single stream recycling.
>> What if we just burn cardboard?
What if we burn it?
Yeah.
The
>> only thing that I would sit there and say related to that is you need to tarp that that
if you if you sit there and allow you have a
a
corrugated
container and it just gets wet, you're just paying excessive
because you can't get the moisture out of the corrugated.
Right.
And
>> it blows all over the place. That's the other problem.
The problem is that's more labor because now you got to put the thing on at the end of the day, and then every time Public Works goes to compact it, you got to go up, you got to get the cover back off, you got to compact it, then you got to put the cover back on, and then the next time you use it, you got to take the cover off. So it's kind of a pain in the butt
any way you cut it.
>> But that's where we're at for now. Are we gonna talk about this next Monday?
>> That would be my guess. But then again, I've kinda already just talked about it. What
what are the do we have
What was our priority list?
>> Well,
you know, we just went over 40% of the budget. The question is, are we going to and do we want other organizations to come in and present their budgets to us? I know Elaine Bucard for economic development, which I know is not a big budget, but she she requested to sit there and
show us her budget. Are there any other departments, Eric, that you want to come and visit with us?
Why don't you do that? Why don't you figure out, Eric, what departments would be good that we hear directly from
those department heads and what their budget presented is for next year, whether I don't care, town clerk, assessor, tax collector, or whatever you want, or you can present all those, and we can go through those sections next week.
>> That's kind of open ended. I mean,
you tell me what you wanna hear. I mean, I
I don't know what you wanna hear or what you wanna know. That's what
>> I'd like to see what the heavy hitters are gonna be. Let's go over all the big let's let's roll up all the increases and go over them.
>> So you wanna go through the wages?
Yeah. Okay.
Anything that's got a substantial increase we should go over because that's that's the that's the low hanging fruit. We should go after that first and look at it because it So you're you're sitting there saying, look at Eric's spreadsheet that he's currently prepared for us and where there there are escalations from last year's budget to this year's budget. Correct.
>> Now do you want it in terms of total dollar priority
in terms of dollar value or priority in terms of percentage increase?
Dollar value.
>> I mean, we should want it in dollar value because
our total,
you know, not a not a percentage of their budget increase or whatever. I mean, if their budget is a $500 budget and they ask for $250
that's a 25 or 50% increase. It's not $250
I don't really care.
But we have a $600,000
total
increase in overall expenditures in Eric's budget that's been, not Eric's, but our budget. And so we just need to understand where those dollars are coming from.
>> Okay. So you want how many? Top 10, top 20?
What do you want presented to you?
And how do you want it presented to you?
Well,
>> what I would do is I would wanna know the total departmental budgets that are increasing,
and then we can sit there and take the top 10.
And then, I mean, but but, you know, you're basically skipping out of j's, all of j's, because he had slight increases across everything.
Yeah. And and and then break it down by that that department. So if you have the top 10 departments or here are the departments or here are the departmental budgets that are increasing, these are the top 10, Here's the amount of money. I mean, I you know, I'd like to know it
in dollars, and then then you drill down on those individual budgets so Jeff and the rest of the team can see what's being spent in that department and why they're increasing so much. And I gotta believe you're not gonna find we're not gonna find a lot of overall increases. It's all gonna be in labor.
That's gonna be our problem, is it's gonna be in labor.
>> Well, I mean, the biggest total
chunk,
really, is capital funds.
I mean, that's your biggest
expenditure,
you know, increase.
That's,
you know, $350,000
out of this. The total is just is capital funds and what we fund and what we don't fund.
>> So out of that $600,000
increase, you're sitting there saying $300,000
of that is related to capital investments.
Beyond the prior year?
Yeah. Compared to the prior year. Yes.
>> Well, we definitely have to see that because that that doesn't make sense to me because it's not like last year we didn't invest.
Yeah.
>> Mhmm. It's like the trees. It's like you're going, okay. The trees don't go up or down because we invested $50,000 last year.
It's not. So,
one, starting
>> a capital fund for AES,
you know, because they're going to have a bunch of capital expenditures,
and we can't absorb that with the current building maintenance fund.
So if you're going to do it, you're going to to
have a funding mechanism for that. Now, part of that should be money they return to the town,
But I don't think that's going to be enough. And I think you're going to have to fund that on an annual basis.
So that's one I think should be done.
The other one, I think off the top
would be
what do you do with the Public Works Equipment Fund? Do you continue
what I proposed,
which is essentially level funding?
Or because Jay is obviously asking for a lot more than what that level funding is.
The second or third big one is bridge and culvert fund.
If we're going to plan on not this year,
but in the following budget,
actually replacing the Lake Road culvert, which is I think about as far off as we can push that,
given that we have
a
agreement through the
state local bridge program,
then we're going to have to up the funding to that from about $100,000
a year to about $175,000
a year. So over the next two years, we can accumulate enough money to do it. So
>> I mean So why don't why don't we start this year?
>> What do you mean start this year? Funding it. Funding it.
We put a 100,000 in this year.
>> Yeah. But if you're saying that we're gonna need a 175, then put in a 150 this year and a 150 next year and a 150 the year after, and then we have it all there. I mean,
spread it out.
Anyway, just bring those next week next week because we're already at 10:00.
So next next next week, we should go over those types of transactions so we understand where the increase
increases that we're going to potentially ask for are coming from.
Because that's gonna be the big thing for us selling this to the residents if we choose to go in that direction. Wages and capital.
That's fine.
>> So you wanna do the top 10 budget increases,
or do you wanna do wages and capital?
>> No. The top 10 budget increases and the wages we can review because
that's a pretty quick review because It is. You know, who who's left? You and Jay.
Right.
Most of it's contracts.
>> And and the librarian and the head librarian, but she's not part of our we don't set that budget. We we can
Well, no. That's not true. You set the budget for for
everybody
other than Amy or Lumosky because there's already an in place
contract for Amy. But everybody else, you set. Alright. So, I mean However,
we're just over the minimum wage. All I'm trying to do with those employees
is get them up enough over the minimum wage so that when they increase the minimum wage next January,
you know, we're not shocked and we're already not having to increase their salary again mid year. Okay.
Let's,
let's do it. Let's pick
>> the top 10 pick the top 10 and actually have
the wage support so we can go over that, because then that will knock out the majority of the big increases, and then we can do
small budgets and then talk about our overall spending, increase or decrease, whatever we choose to do. Because if we decide to decrease from what people are asking from, which we probably will in some aspects, we just got to make where those cuts are coming.
It's like going to Jay and go, okay, we're going to cut you here, cut you here. And
the other part that we need to know or we should see is
current expenditures versus the prior year budget, so we understand these departments in these areas and where they're currently at.
Okay. Anybody have any other problems?
>> Okay. So I will get you the spreadsheet
of
not this current budget year,
but the budget year previous,
what was actually spent by each department. So I'll get you that, and I'll get you year to date spending
for all the budgets
for this current year.
And then I will get you
essentially a list of the top 10 departments.
And you've already got the wage information.
Right? Does that sound like a reasonable?
What your expectations
>> are? Correct. And we do have the wage information, but we can also just
review,
know, the wages are just going to increase. I mean, they're going to increase based upon the contracts.
We should talk separately
about the
ones like
your compensation, Eric, and Jay's compensation, because I know there was a note in our package related to Jay
that we should review separately other than from his budget. Because we'll have to talk about that. Yep.
Yep. Anybody
>> else have anything they want Eric to get ready for next week?
Yay, budget season.
>> Yeah, we're working on it.
I know we don't have public speak
after this, but is everybody good with where we're at for the workshop aspect of this?
Let a public speak. Joanne Ebert, do you have anything to say?
>> Thanks, Jeff. I won't keep you guys. It's been a long meeting.
Just I did want to say that
I was very, very disappointed like Jeff Murray with that contractor that they used for the I know that the tree not the tree work, but the road work is so important in town.
I learn about it. But living on Bear Swamp Road and waiting for it for the longest time,
we had a horrible
experience with it, with everything
you all said.
And I hope
you know, I'm going to ask Eric again. He gave me an example of a road to go down where it does look good. I think he said Burnout Brook.
Yeah, because whatever was done on our road, I would have rather saved up and enough money to just repave and
that kind of thing. So, we were one of those. I have other thoughts, but I won't bore you all with them now.
I'll try to get my head around it
for public speak the next time. Thank you.
Right.
>> Okay. Thank you very much.
And now we'll go to our last item. So we have a meeting next Monday,
correct? Next Monday. And then the following week, we have our regular scheduled meeting. And then do we have a meeting scheduled for the Tuesday after our regular meeting? Well, I think it's on You took that week off, right? No, I think it's on Wednesday.
Oh, killing me. Yeah.
Okay.
No rest for the weary. No. Let's sit there and do it. So, alright. Does somebody wanna make a motion to adjourn? Motion to adjourn.
Alright. Second. Second.
Scott, second the ballot. Alright. All those in favor?
Aye.
Jeff Murray, you voting?
A rush for the wicked. Voted yes. We're just gonna say Jeff Murray voted yes. Alright.
Right. Thank you, Eric, for all your hard work. Appreciate it.
You are welcome. Have a happy evening.
Yeah. Bye bye. Good night. Good night.